GPS on smartphones is really convenient, isn't it?
手機的GPS真的很方便對吧？
I'm embarrassed to admit I have a terrible sense of direction
說來慚愧，我是個路痴
Without GPS and smartphone map apps I can barely get to my destination
沒有GPS和手機地圖App的話 我連目的地都很難到達
But GPS relies on signals from space
但GPS畢竟是依賴來自太空的訊號
It doesn't work when you're in a tunnel or on a ferry out at sea
在隧道裡的時候 或是搭渡輪在海上的時候就無法使用
And it can be disabled by malicious jamming signals
而且惡意的干擾電波也會讓它失效
But is there a way to measure position with high precision without GPS?
但是有沒有不用GPS也能超高精度測量位置的方法呢？
Actually, a technology called quantum navigation using ultra-cold atoms is rapidly developing
其實現在有一種使用超低溫原子的 量子導航技術正在快速發展
In 2025, there was news that Boeing and the British Navy succeeded in demonstration tests
2025年波音公司和英國海軍 已經成功完成實證實驗的消息也傳出來了
Today, I'll explain why cooling atoms allows us to determine position
今天我要來解說為什麼冷卻原子 就能知道位置
Let's look at how it works
讓我們來看看它的原理
First, let's talk about the most classical method of knowing your position without GPS
首先來談談不使用GPS 就能知道自己位置的最古老方法
Have you ever heard of the speed unit called "knots"?
大家有聽過「節」這個速度單位嗎？
It's used for ship speeds, right?
是用來表示船速的對吧？
This unit actually comes from a measurement method invented by ancient sailors
這個單位其實源自古代水手發明的測量方法
They tied knots at regular intervals on a rope
在繩子上以固定間隔打結
And threw it into the sea
然後把它丟進海裡
They counted how many knots passed while the sand in an hourglass fell
數一數在沙漏落下的期間 有多少個結流過去
This told them their speed
這樣就能知道速度了
It's a really clever method, isn't it?
是個很聰明的方法對吧？
Distance traveled can be calculated by multiplying speed and time
移動距離可以用速度乘以時間來計算
It's a formula you learn in middle school but this is the basis of inertial navigation
這是國中學過的公式 也是慣性導航的基礎
But in real movement, speed changes, right?
但實際移動時速度會改變對吧？
Accelerating and decelerating
加速或減速
In that case, you can plot speed versus time on a graph and find the distance traveled from the area under the curve
這種情況下畫出速度與時間的圖表 求出面積就能得到移動距離
This is what we call integration in mathematics
這就是數學上所說的積分
But modern aircraft and ships commonly measure acceleration rather than velocity to determine position
但現代的飛機和船舶通常是測量加速度 而不是速度來確定位置
Why measure acceleration instead of velocity?
為什麼要測量加速度而不是速度呢？
When you're on an airplane you feel takeoff and landing with your body, right?
搭飛機的時候 起飛和降落的瞬間你會用身體感受到對吧？
But during stable flight, you can't even tell if you're moving without looking out the window
但在穩定飛行中如果不看窗外 甚至不知道自己是否在移動
In other words, it's difficult to directly measure velocity inside a vehicle moving at constant speed
也就是說在等速運動的交通工具中 很難直接測量速度
Measuring velocity requires an external reference
測量速度需要外部參照
But acceleration can be measured without an external reference
但加速度不需要外部參照就能測量
That's why inertial navigation measures acceleration and integrates it twice to find position
所以慣性導航是測量加速度 然後積分兩次來求得位置
It's a self-contained system that can work on its own without external information
這是一個不需要外部資訊 能夠自己完成的自足系統
But there's a big problem here
但這裡有一個大問題
If there's a slight error in the accelerometer that error accumulates with each integration
如果加速度計有微小的誤差 每次積分這個誤差就會累積
Moreover, since distance is calculated by integrating acceleration twice, the error grows proportionally to the square of time
而且因為距離是將加速度積分兩次計算的 誤差會與時間的平方成正比增加
Even with today's high-precision aircraft accelerometers the error reaches about 6.5 km after 10 hours
即使是現在航空用的高精度加速度計 10小時後誤差也會達到約6.5公里
This makes it unusable for long-distance navigation
這樣就無法用於長距離航行了
That's why we currently use GPS corrections periodically to reset the error
所以現在是透過GPS定期校正 來重置誤差
Aircraft, ships, smartphones - they all use this method
飛機、船舶、智慧型手機都是用這種方式
So current positioning technology requires external information like GPS
所以現在的定位技術 需要像GPS這樣的外部資訊
But GPS has weaknesses too
但GPS也有弱點
Since it uses radio waves from satellites naturally it can't work where signals can't reach
因為使用衛星的電波 當然在訊號無法到達的地方就無法使用
For example, underwater
例如水中
GPS cannot measure the position of submarines or underwater drones
潛水艇或水下無人機的位置無法用GPS測量
It also doesn't work in tunnels, underground spaces, or urban canyons
在隧道、地下空間或都市峽谷中也無法使用
What's even scarier is malicious attacks
更可怕的是惡意攻擊
Spoofing sends fake GPS signals to cause position errors and jamming disables GPS with interference signals
欺騙攻擊會發送假的GPS訊號導致位置錯誤 干擾攻擊則用干擾電波讓GPS失效
These are real threats in conflict zones and near borders
在衝突地區及其邊境附近這是現實的威脅
This is where quantum mechanics comes in
這就是量子力學登場的時候了
In 1924, a physicist named Louis de Broglie proposed a remarkable theory
1924年一位名叫路易·德布羅意的物理學家 提出了驚人的理論
"All matter has wave-like properties" This is called matter waves
「所有物質都具有波的性質」 這被稱為物質波
The wavelength λ can be expressed by this formula
波長λ可以用這個公式表示
h is Planck's constant, m is mass, v is velocity In other words, slower-moving objects have longer wavelengths
h是普朗克常數、m是質量、v是速度 也就是說移動越慢的物體波長越長
Just as light, which was thought to be a wave also has particle-like properties
就像被認為是波的光 同時也具有粒子的性質一樣
Atoms, which were thought to be particles also have wave-like properties at the same time
被認為是粒子的原子 同時也具有波的性質
Have you ever seen light interference patterns?
你看過光的干涉條紋嗎？
When light waves with matching wavelengths collide they create bright and dark stripe patterns
當波長相同的光波相遇時 會產生明暗相間的條紋圖案
Since atoms also have wave properties, they can do the same thing but there's a problem as they are
因為原子也有波的性質所以也能做到同樣的事 但原本的狀態有問題
Hot atoms move at random velocities
熱的原子以隨機速度運動
Random velocities mean random wavelengths
速度隨機意味著波長也隨機
This causes the interference pattern to blur
這樣干涉條紋就會模糊
That's why we cool the atoms
所以要冷卻原子
Cooling slows them down and narrows the velocity distribution
冷卻後運動變慢速度分布變窄
The wavelengths align
波長就統一了
Only then can we create clean interference
這樣才能產生清晰的干涉
But how do you cool atoms?
但要怎麼冷卻原子呢？
Do you put them in a freezer?
放進冷凍庫冷卻嗎？
Actually, we use a literally cooler method
其實我們使用的方法真的很「酷」
We cool them using lasers
我們用雷射來冷卻
When an atom absorbs a photon, it receives the photon's momentum and gets pushed
當原子吸收光子時會接收光子的動量而被推動
If we shine a laser opposite to the atom's direction of travel, the atom slows down
如果從原子前進方向的反方向照射雷射，原子就會減速
We can also selectively slow only fast atoms using the Doppler effect
利用都卜勒效應還能選擇性地只減速快速原子
Approaching atoms see a higher frequency and resonate
接近的原子看到較高的頻率所以會共振
Receding atoms see a lower frequency and don't resonate
遠離的原子看到較低的頻率所以不會共振
With laser cooling, we can reach temperatures very close to absolute zero -273.15 degrees Celsius
使用雷射冷卻可以達到接近絕對零度 攝氏-273.15度的溫度
We can make it colder than outer space
可以比外太空還要冷
So what do we do with these cooled atoms?
那麼冷卻後的原子要做什麼呢？
Now we move from cooling to a different laser operation
接下來是與冷卻不同的雷射操作
We make the cooled atoms interfere to measure acceleration
讓冷卻的原子產生干涉 來測量加速度
There's a light-based interferometer called the Mach-Zehnder interferometer
有一種使用光的干涉儀 叫做馬赫-曾德爾干涉儀
Light is split into two paths by a half-mirror
用半反射鏡將光分成兩條路徑
The light from each path is then recombined
然後讓經過各路徑的光再次合流
When there's a path difference, interference patterns form
這時如果有路徑差就會產生干涉條紋
Atom interferometers work on the same principle
原子干涉儀的基本原理相同
The key point is that laser pulses can manipulate atomic paths
重點是雷射脈衝可以操控原子的路徑
Applying laser pulses corresponds to splitting light at a half-mirror or reflecting off a mirror
照射雷射的操作可以對應到 半反射鏡的光分離或鏡子的反射
When two lasers with slightly different frequencies hit an atom the atom's internal state and momentum change simultaneously
當兩束頻率略有不同的雷射照射原子時 原子的內部狀態和動量會同時改變
This is called Raman transition
這叫做拉曼躍遷
By controlling the atomic path with lasers
透過雷射控制原子前進的路徑
We can create interference due to path differences
可以產生因路徑差而造成的干涉
Atom interferometers use three laser pulses
原子干涉儀使用三次雷射脈衝
The first laser pulse splits the atom creating a superposition of ground state |g⟩ and excited state |e⟩
第一次雷射脈衝分割原子 產生基態|g⟩和激發態|e⟩的疊加態
It serves the same role as a half-mirror in optical systems
作用與光學系統中的半反射鏡相同
The second laser pulse reverses the paths
第二次雷射脈衝反轉路徑
It swaps the ground state |g⟩ and excited state |e⟩
將基態|g⟩和激發態|e⟩互換
This corresponds to mirror reflection in optical systems
對應於光學系統中的鏡面反射
The final laser pulse superimposes the two paths to create interference
最後一次雷射脈衝 將兩條路徑疊加產生干涉
It serves as a half-mirror, just like the first pulse
與第一次一樣扮演半反射鏡的角色
In this way, three laser pulses can realize a Mach-Zehnder interferometer with atoms
這樣透過三次雷射脈衝 就能用原子實現馬赫-曾德爾干涉儀
If there's acceleration the two paths experience different force histories
如果有加速度 通過兩條路徑的原子受力歷程就會不同
This difference appears as a phase shift
這個差異會表現為相位差
The phase difference Δφ can be written as this formula
相位差Δφ可以用這個公式表示
This phase difference can ultimately be observed as the probability of being in ground state |g⟩
這個相位差最終可以作為 處於基態|g⟩的機率來觀測
By using many atoms and measuring statistically we can determine the acceleration
使用大量原子進行統計測量 就能得知加速度
Comparing with conventional MEMS accelerometers shows that atom interferometers have extremely high precision
與傳統MEMS加速度計相比 可以看出原子干涉儀的精度極高
The precision of atom interferometers is around 10⁻⁹ to 10⁻¹² m/s²
原子干涉儀的精度大約在 10⁻⁹到10⁻¹² m/s²左右
This means an error of only about 65 cm for a 10-hour flight
這樣10小時的飛行誤差只有約65公分
Long-duration high-precision positioning is possible without GPS
不用GPS也能實現長時間高精度的位置測量
Atom interferometers are based on atomic transition frequencies which are fundamental constants of nature
原子干涉儀是以原子躍遷頻率 這個自然基本常數為基準
Planck's constant and the speed of light are the same everywhere in the universe, at all times
普朗克常數和光速 在宇宙任何地方任何時候都相同
That's why such precise measurements are possible
所以才能實現高精度測量
You might be thinking "It might work in theory but can it really be put into practical use?"
你可能會想「理論上也許可行 但真的能實用化嗎？」
Actually, demonstration tests have already succeeded
其實實證實驗已經成功了
Boeing, the famous aircraft manufacturer achieved a 4-hour GPS-free flight in 2025
知名飛機製造商波音公司 在2025年成功完成了4小時無GPS飛行
Q-CTRL, an Australian startup company achieved 22m precision with a Cessna aircraft
澳洲新創公司Q-CTRL 用塞斯納飛機達到了22公尺的精度
They won Time magazine's 2025 Best Inventions award
並獲得了時代雜誌2025年最佳發明獎
The British Navy has also succeeded in submarine tests
英國海軍也在潛水艇測試中取得成功
While still in the research stage it's attracting worldwide attention as next-generation positioning technology
雖然還在研究階段 但作為下一代定位技術正受到全球矚目
There are still many challenges like device miniaturization and cost reduction
裝置小型化和成本降低等課題還有很多
But advances in semiconductor lasers and atom chip technology used in quantum computers are bringing it closer to practical use each year
但隨著半導體雷射的進步和量子電腦也在應用的 原子晶片技術的發展，每年都在接近實用化
Quantum mechanics might seem like a mysterious and strange world
量子力學可能給人一種 神秘世界的印象
But like quantum navigation it's working as the foundation for technologies that benefit our daily lives
但像量子導航這樣 正在成為有益於我們日常生活的技術基礎
Just as smartphone GPS became commonplace
就像智慧型手機的GPS變得理所當然一樣
Quantum navigation might become commonplace someday too
也許有一天量子導航也會變得理所當然
Until next time, take care!
那麼下次影片再見，再見！